[Music]
what is the best book what is the best
techbook to learn from um this is a
tough question because it depends on
what you want to do right there are Tech
reference books which I'll do a separate
video about and then there are Tech
books that are designed to specifically
to help you learn and if I had one
criticism of the techbook industry in
general it's that so many books don't
know what they want to be
um you have the recipe books from
O'Reilly which are really amazing um you
know I depended on those during my
career um in fact Unix in a nutshell was
the very first O'Reilly book I ever
owned I still have it somewhere it's a
collector's item at this point and it
was amazing right but did it really I
remember reading it it felt like I was
reading a
dictionary right um there are a bunch of
academic books which are kind of outside
both of these
categories um thank you for the sub we
have academic books which are not
written for the learner at all they're
written for the person that's going to
force the people learning to buy the
book and I I not including those C in
the category unfortunately they're
overpriced and people have to buy them
there's a there's a rant I made about
whether you should pay or for books or
not in a separate video go watch that um
if you want to hear me rant more about
the horrible economy of academic writing
I think it's a disaster I think it's I
don't want to go talk about it it's very
negative so what are the good books the
good books are books like this one head
first SE now when I first encountered
this very very silly book um you know I
was very skeptical you got to understand
I am a guy who comes from a sort of the
tradition of like hey if it's not a
serious book it's not a serious thing
you know and yes I do believe that you
read The Bash man page to learn bash you
know rtfm read the fancy manual a lot of
times you don't need a book at all um
but you know on occasion a book is
extremely valuable and it was It was
kind of fun to realize that the head for
C Series when I read the introduction to
it and I will read it to you now um that
it was consistent with what I had been
doing at skill stack for a long time so
something I learned completely
organically without any training at all
was if I wanted learning to stick um in
you know these 9 to 19 year olds brains
that I needed to make it fun it turns
out that there's a lot of science behind
this there's dopamine uh that causes
learning to happen and there's you know
and it's actually itemized a little bit
and something I'm about to read here but
there are a lot of reasons that that
remembering things putting things in
story form making we used to use memes
we will use memes in fact if you uh
check out the other videos which I
haven't made yet on learning to code and
polyglot approach learning python
JavaScript and go at the same time we
going to be coding some very silly memes
um because honest to this is exactly how
it happened I'm going to tell you the
story and then I'll tell you why I think
these books are so valuable because of
it so a lot of times again organic
learning happens in the lab not the
lecture hall that's a quote I would like
to put on my wall someplace because the
lab is where you get to experiment and
fail and try and have fun and no
pressure right it's not somebody up
there like telling you yeah memes are
even a job now um it's not somebody up
there telling you you know flexing and
showing all kinds of academic you know
prowess or whatever you're they don't
care about you they just want to flex
and you know the lab is where people get
excited about learning and stuff like
that right so anyway given that
atmosphere and I made other videos about
that but people were coming to me and
they're coming into my lab and sure
they're paying your parents are paying
50 bucks an hour or something but they
still want to have fun and they've been
you know they've been at school all day
and they don't really want to come and
sit in another school class so I said
okay what are we G to do today guys
let's have fun and they're like oh let's
let's code the waffle song I know that's
really dating me it's a really old meme
um and I what the W what's the waffle
song you know one time they said hey
let's code let's code Llamas with Hats
which is totally disgusting and
inappropriate and we're not going to do
it but you know another time time they
were like well let's code this and I
said oh how about we Cod this one let's
let's code let's code the bridgekeeper
and they're like What's the bridgekeeper
and I showed him Monty Python
bridgekeeper skit and they're like oh my
God that's so awesome so our educational
time together became an exchange of
memes and fun video clips um that then
we would say well what can we code how
can we code that right and Badgers we
coded the badger song ones to do you
know numbered loops and thing I was like
well what what principle from
programming can associate with this meme
with this fun thing that these kids want
to do and and and we we we would
constantly find you know they would come
in and say let's code but because they
were their
life revolved around memes which still
is true for a lot of young people and so
we would we would make all kinds of
different weird things and um and it was
really fun and and and they remembered
it and actually Whit came up to me
several years later
um I've told the story before I'm tell
it again but he came up to me several
years later then we're talking about
after he got a Sy system administrator
job at 16 um I mean he was extremely
talented he was running all the
Minecraft servers and everything he he
taught himself uh all kinds of different
things with the languages and um had
evaluated you know kubernetes versus uh
do swarm on his own at like 15 I mean if
you know what these things are you know
that this guy had had really blossomed
and and he came back to me some years
later and he said you know Mr Rob you
know what really worked for me when you
did those micro projects those little
meme projects and he and this is his
direct feedback he said when you did
that when I couldn't remember something
I remembered the meme that went with it
I remembered the meme and I was able to
pull the meme up and and then I could
actually go find the meme in my GitHub
where I had coded it in my private repo
and I could remind myself how I did it
and it came back to my memory much
easier and that my friends is how
learning happens and that is the basis
of the brain friendly guides coming from
O'Reilly and when I read that when I
read that I was immediately on board as
silly as it was I was like oh I see
they're using actual pedagogical
scientific
studies that have shown that this
actually
works and so here you read right here it
says um we think your time is too
valuable to waste struggling with new
Concepts using the latest research in
cognitive science and learning theory to
Corp a multi- sensory learning
experience that is what I was doing
organically and on accident by observing
in what I call the Learning lab where
learning I was learning about learning
and laboratory environment and I was
able to adjust how the learning was
happening based on what worked and what
didn't so you know they were learning in
a learning lab and I was learning in a
learning lab I was learning about
learning and one of the things I learned
about learning was that a multi- sensory
you know mem driven sort of learning
experience helped it to stick better and
it made it fun we had a blast in there
we would put music on we would take
musical breaks and we dance around like
crazy people I did not know that all the
dopamine that was being produced by that
entire experience was solidifying the
learning that they were doing and giving
them solid
pneum pneumonic that I said right memory
things to grab on to in their memory it
turns out also by the way my friends
that the people who memorize pi to like
a 100 digits or whatever these people
who have memory competitions guess how
they do it they make a story they
imagine a story a visual story the C
easier the better in their head and then
they tell themselves that story and they
associate a number with each one that's
how they win those competitions they do
it through multisensory learning by
creating our St because our brains are
designed to do stories that's why we
like to be to hear stories when we're
taught and um and and all of that so so
when we read here that head per se
usually uh uses a visually Rich format
design for the way your brain works not
a text Heavy approach that puts you to
sleep and this is the point where I'm
going to defend my criticism of k andrc
um people who are the authorities on a
particular language uh or or system are
often the worst people on the planet to
write a book about it because they are
going to give you this really boring put
you to sleep thing and everybody's going
to call it the Bible I learned from
KRC um yeah Moon walking with Einstein
the Art and Science of remembering
everything is a cool book on that that's
so Co that's very very cool book um
thank you for the recommendation so so
when I you know again what I was
skeptical of these books when I first
saw them and this approach in general I
was skeptical of it because it looks
really silly let me show you like when
you when you go into the book you're
like what this is I I've got it's all
kind of reversed because I don't want to
Blind you but look at how silly it is
right who is this book for do you
already know programming I can't believe
you put see in this book it's got these
really really silly things in here right
so here he goes it says uh we know what
your brain is thinking your brain craves
novelty it's what it it always searches
scanning waiting for something unusual
this is why memes are so popular it was
built that way and it helps you stay
alive so what does your brain do with
the routine ordinary normal things you
encounter everything everything it can
to stop them from interfering with the
brain's real job recording things that
matter it doesn't bother saving saving
the boring things they'll never make it
past that this is obviously not
important filter so how does your brain
know what's important suppose you're out
for a Day hike and the tiger jumps in
front of you what happens inside your
head and your body neurons fire emotions
crank up chemical Surge and that's how
your brain knows this must be important
don't forget it but imagine your home in
the library it's safe warm tiger free
zone you're studying trying to get ready
for an exam one thing um or trying to
learn some tough topic technically 10
days that would take a week or 10 days
of the most just one problem your
brain's your brain's trying to do a
bigger favor is trying to make sure that
that this is obviously unimportant
content doesn't cut up to spaces and
you're falling
asleep resources are better storing
things that really matter like tigers
the dangers of life like the fun stuff
like how you should never be posted
these party photos on your Facebook page
there's no simple way to tell your brain
hey brain thank you very much but no
matter how dull this book is and how
little I'm in registering this emotional
re rer Ricker scale right now I really
do want to keep this stuff
around so so that's what it says here
what we think of the head for as a
learner
uh so what does it take to learn
something first of all you need to get
it you if you're going to get it you
need to not forget it and how do you
remember it that comes back to the
visual Imaging some of the head first
principles make it visual images are far
more memorable than words alone make it
much more effective uh use a
conversational personal personalized
style and this by the way shapes
everything that I've ever done uh I want
to keep it personal I if I can pick a
big word and I'm use a simple word if
I'm going to do the big word I'm going
to you know tell tell you what the big
word means um you know and it says get
the learner to think more deeply um they
don't actually say this but it says
right here get and keep the reader
attention and touch their emotions there
is something that's implied in that that
they're not saying and that is
storytelling storytelling is used to
memorize the pi out to 100 digits it's
also used to convey meaning to the brain
from one human to another we think in
narrative that's that's how we are
operated it's the reason that we binge
watch Netflix or whatever we are
designed we are we we like story we like
narrative and the more visual the better
the more imaginative the better so you
know if you can put something into a
role playay they will learn it better
every time every time and I was a big D
and D guy I also use roleplay to help
train Mormon missionaries I'm not Mormon
anymore but it was very effective right
because people were able to play out a
story in their brain
interactively and remember it with an
experience and a lot of people think
that this is why gaming is such a
powerful way to do education as well
because you are creating actual
narrative experiences in a visual pseudo
physical environment where people can
can can you know they can other the
neurons in their brain are going to
trigger to remember the the principle
behind it because there's so much else
going on uh in that time you think it
would be the distraction it's actually
actually not if if it's associated with
the thing they're learning then it turns
into
metacognition thinking about thinking
and this is why the head for series is
is is superior to everything else in my
book uh for learning specifically for
learning it says here the final thing
the trick is to get your brain to see
the new material you're learning as
really important crucial to your
well-being as important as a tiger uh
otherwise you're in for a constant
battle with your brain doing its best to
keep new content foring another way to
make it stick in your brain is is we we
assign a lot of importance to things
that are funny you know the reason that
these the you know the story I told with
the the kids coming in and saying hey Mr
Rob have you seen the latest meme
because to them that's important right
that's something worth remembering if I
don't remember this meme people are
going to laugh at me or or I like it
because it's entertaining and so whether
it's a meme or it's you know it's a
silly image or whatever it is that's
that's what you're going to remember and
that's the way to do the learning and
that's why I am a big fan of the head
first series because they have taken the
most recent discoveries in learning
theory and they have gotten totally on
board with it despite immense criticism
from the academic world because academic
books are going to put you to sleep and
empty your wallet these these books
aren't and this this approach is going
to keep you stimulated this I'm also
going to refer back to this video when
we do you know python bridgekeeper um or
or you know badgers or we ask hey is
there a meme that you guys want to code
you know let's let's code it and let's
associate the latest funny silly meme
with something specifically about your
learning so that you can take it with
you and prosper and win and you know
dominate the day so